Finding Aid for Women of Color Task Force (University of Michigan) records, 1979-2008
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Women of Color Task Force (University of Michigan) records 1979-2008
University of Michigan. Women of Color Task Force.
64 KB
6 linear feet
88289 Bimu B28 2
Support group founded at the University of Michigan to aid minority women employed as office and professional staff members in combating racial and sexist stereotypes and in providing counsel on matters of career planning, job hunting, and development of communication skills. Records include subject files detailing activities of the Task Force, especially to those conferences it sponsored; also history, minutes, correspondence, photographs, publicity, publications, and videotapes.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were received in periodic accessions beginning in 1988 (Donor # 7517 ).
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The record group is open for research.
In 1979, Jennie Partee of the University of Michigan Affirmative Action Office and Beulah Sanders of the School of Education began offering career workshops for minority women several times a year. The stated purpose of the workshops was "to provide employees who are women of color with skills and confidence to move upward within the organization, both for their own benefit and to benefit the University by creating a more truly diverse and therefore enriched work force" (Box 1, History folder, "The History of the Minority Women's Task Force"). The workshops were aimed at both professionals and nonprofessionals and focused on practical topics such as communication skills and job hunting. A minority women's group developed from these workshops, sponsored by the Affirmative Action Office, the Human Resource Development Office, and the Medical Campus Office of Training and Development.
In 1982 the group officially became the Minority Women's Task Force and in 1983 held its first annual all-day Minority Women's Career Conference, which included speakers as well as workshops. Very similar to the career workshops, the conference had the added objectives of promoting a network among minority women at the university, sharing information and raising consciousness on common issues, and increasing the visibility of minority women. Entirely planned by volunteers on the Task Force, the annual conference has become the main activity of the group. The conferences grew from eleven workshops and 200 participants in 1983 to 45 workshops and 701 participants in 1989. Nearly 1000 people attended the 1992 conference, which was sponsored by the Affirmative Action Office, Medical Campus Human Resource Development, the Office of Human Resource Development and the Office of Minority Affairs.
In 1984 the Task Force implemented the Partee-Sanders Scholarship Fund, in honor of its two founders. In 1986 an awards program was established to recognize outstanding university women in human relations, leadership, and distinguished service in the Task Force. That same year the group changed its name to the Women of Color Task Force (WCTF), both to avoid the negative connotations of the word "minority" and to emphasize that it was concerned with women of all ethnic minority groups. In 1990 the WCTF broadened its purview to include women not only on the Ann Arbor campus, but on the Dearborn and Flint campuses as well, and began including a separate program for men of color during its annual conference, hoping to foster a male counterpart to the Task Force.
The Women of Color Task Force (WCTF) records include subject files detailing activities of the Task Force, especially to those conferences it sponsored; also history, minutes, correspondence, photographs, publicity, publications, and videotapes. The Women of Color Task Force (WCTF) records are divided into three series: Administrative, Events and Audio-Visual
Subjects:
University of Michigan--Employees.; University of Michigan. Women of Color Task Force.; African Americans--Michigan.; Women--Employment--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
African Americans--Organizations.; African Americans--Women.; Minorities.; Women--Employment--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Employees.; University of Michigan. Women of Color Task Force.
Genre Terms:
College publications.; Photographs.; Videotapes.
- Administrative
  The Administrative series is arranged alphabetically by topic and consists of minutes, committees and annual conferences among others. The Agendas and Minutes reflect the issues discussed and business conducted (ranging from conference planning to administrative logistics) during the weekly meetings of the Task Force co-chairs and planning members. Because they form an almost complete set, the Agendas and Minutes offer a good view of the day-to-day workings of the WCTF. The history, mission and bylaws, and organizational structure of the WCTF can also be found in this series.
  - Agendas and Minutes 1982-1996, 15 folders (Box 1)
  - Budget 1983-1995 (Box 1)
  - Bylaws and Mission 1991-1994 (Box 1)
  - Committees
    - General Information 1986-1996 (Box 1)
    - Awards/Selection Committee 1989, 1995-1997 (Box 1)
    - Executive Committee 1990-1993 (Box 1)
    - Facilities Committee 1991-1993 (Box 1)
    - Financial Development Committee 1992 (Box 1)
    - Historical Committee 1987-1994 (Box 1)
    - Membership Committee 1992, 1994-1995 (Box 1)
    - Outreach Committee 1990-1993 (Box 1)
    - Program Development Committee 1988-1992 (Box 1)
    - Publicity Committee 1989-1990, 1995 (Box 1)
    - Resource Table Committee 1991-1994 (Box 1)
    - Strategic Planning Executive Advisory Committee 1989-1991 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - 1983-1994, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - 1996-1997, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Elections 1991 (Box 2)
  - History 1983-1995 (Box 2)
  - Meeting with President Duderstadt 1994 (Box 2)
  - Organizational Structure and Directories 1987-1991 (Box 2)
  - Partee Sanders Educational Assistance Fund 1985, 1989-1991 (Box 2)
  - Vendors 1996 (Box 2)
- Events
  The Events series contains the activities that WCTF organizes for its members. The biggest activity of the Task Force is the Annual Career Conference. Each year the conference has a specific topic in which all the sessions and workshops are concentrate. The conferences' records include programs, planning and evaluative reports. In addition to the career conferences, this series contains records of the Annual Awards of WCTF, with programs, information about nominees and winners. The Events series also includes information about retreats and luncheons.
  - Annual Awards
    - General 1989-1994 (Box 2)
    - Purpose and Criteria 1986 (Box 2)
    - Planning 1988-1994, 1998 (Box 2)
    - Programs 1992, 1998 (Box 2)
    - Reports and Budgets 1986-1987 (Box 2)
    - Awards
      - Human Relations
        - Nominations 1987 (Box 2)
        - Winners 1988, 1992-1994 (except 1992) (Box 2)
      - Leadership
        - Nominations
          - 1987 (Box 2)
          - 1996 (Box 2)
        - Winners 1987, 1989-1994 (except 1992) (Box 2)
      - Rebecca A. Vaugh Distinguished Service
        - Nominations 1987, 1991 (Box 2)
        - Winners 1987-1993 (except 1992) (Box 2)
      - Woman of the Year, 2003-2004, 2006 (except 1992) (Box 2)
  - Annual Career Conferences
    - 1983-1984, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - "Women of Color: Striving for Excellence" 1985 (Box 2)
    - "Focus On: Effectiveness, Productivity and Professionalism"
      - General Information 1986 (Box 2)
      - Reports and Evaluations 1986 (Box 2)
    - "Working Constructively Toward the Future: If You Think You Can, You Can"
      - General Information 1987 (Box 2)
      - Planning 1986-1987 (Box 2)
      - Reports and Evaluations 1987 (Box 2)
    - "Imagine What We Can Be: Challenge, Create, Celebrate" 1988 (Box 2)
    - "Shades of Quality: Emerging, Excelling, Empowering"
      - General Information 1989 (Box 2)
      - Planning 1988-1989 (Box 2)
    - "Progressing Towards Plurality: The Challenge of the 90's"
      - General Information 1990 (Box 2)
      - Planning 1989-1990 (Box 2)
    - "See Beyond Today: Inspiring a Vision to Enhance the Quality of Life" (Box 3)
      - General Information 1991 (Box 3)
      - Planning 1990-1991 (Box 3)
    - "Ten Years in Retrospect: Commemorating Our Past, Securing Our Future"
      - General Information 1992 (Box 3)
      - Planning 1991-1992 (Box 3)
      - Final Report and Evaluation 1992 (Box 3)
    - "Globally Pulling Our Cultures Together"
      - General Information 1993 (Box 3)
      - Planning 1992-1993 (Box 3)
    - "Developing a Plan for Excellence" 1994 (Box 3)
    - "Success: Beginning with the End in Mind"
      - General Information 1995 (Box 3)
      - Planning 1994-1995 (Box 3)
      - Final Report 1995 (Box 3)
    - "Building and Creating Opportunities for Growth" 1996 (Box 3)
    - "Looking Back, Moving Forward"
      - General Information 1996-1997 (Box 3)
      - Workshops 1997 (Box 3)
      - Speakers' Bibliographical Statements 1997 (Box 3)
      - Final Report 1997 (Box 3)
    - 1998-2000 (Box 3)
  - Luncheons and Recruitment, 1988-1993 (Box 3)
  - Luncheons and Recruitment, 2003-2005 (Box 3)
  - Members Summer Retreat, 2003-2006, 2008, 5 folders (Box 3)
  - Retreats, 1990-1993 (Box 3)
  - Town Meeting, 1995 (Box 3)
  - Workshops, Minority Women's Career
    - 1979-1982 (Box 3)
    - 1983-1985 and 1991 (Box 3)
  - Workshops and Programs, 2004-2006, 2008, 4 folders (Box 3)
- Audio-Visual
  The Audio-Visual series is comprised of twenty-five numbered audiotapes (cassette format) in two groups: workshops and interviews. Within each group the tapes are arranged chronologically. The name of each workshop leader (if known) is in the folder list. While not a complete set of every conference workshop, the audiotapes provide a valuable window into the concerns and problems of modern women of color because the workshops were forums where these women could speak freely. The interviews are with Woman of the Year award winners or with women influential in the WCTF. The series also contains thirteen videotapes (mostly in U-matic format, but one is in VHS format), which document the annual career conferences and fashion shows from 1985 to 1989. Photographs and slides also document the conferences.
  - Audiotapes (cassettes)
    - Conference Workshops (Box 4)
      - Undated
        - 1) Executive Secretary (Box 4)
        - 2) Overcoming Cultural Barriers (Box 4)
        - 3) Working Mothers' Children (Sharon Jordan) (Box 4)
        - 4) Wellness: Staying Fit Part I (Daphne Jones) (Box 4)
        - 5) Wellness: Staying Fit Part II (Daphne Jones) (Box 4)
      - 1985
        - 6) Dual Career Couples (Verdun and Ingram) (Box 4)
        - 7) Health Care Professionals (Box 4)
        - 8) Interviewing Skills (G. Edwards and E. Lewis) (Box 4)
        - 9) Moving on Up: Career Development for Service and Maintenance (Grace Willis) (Box 4)
        - 10) Performance Planning, and Evaluation (Laurita Thomas) (Box 4)
        - 11) Personal Financial Planning (Sheryl White) (Box 4)
        - 12) Racism and Sexism III (Dottie Jones and Trudy Sims) (Box 4)
        - 13) Women in Science, Math and Engineering Careers (Box 4)
      - 1986
        - 14) Mentoring (Alta Gaines) (Box 4)
        - 15) Nonverbal Communication (Ruby Beale) (Box 4)
        - 16) Strategic Life Planning (Francine Lundy), side B; Professional Development, keynote address, (Dr. Elizabeth Allen), side A (Box 4)
        - 17) Strategies for Career Success (Denise Bristol) (Box 4)
    - Interviews
      - 1985
        - 18) Haywood, Zina R. (Box 4)
        - 19) Peterson, Stephanie (Box 4)
      - 1986
        - 20) Craig, Mayble (Box 4)
        - 21) Holt, Carlitha (Box 4)
        - 22) Johnson, Sally (Box 4)
        - 23) Spencer, Georgene (Box 4)
        - 24) Tirado, Millie (Box 4)
      - 1987
        - 25) Craig, Mayble (Box 4)
  - Photographs
    - Career Conferences, Annual
      - 1984-1985 (Box 4)
      - 1986 (Box 4)
      - 1987 (Box 4)
      - 1988 (Box 4)
      - 1989-1992 (Box 4)
      - 1993 (Box 4)
      - miscellaneous circa 1990 (Box 4)
    - Slides circa 1985 (in color; various WCTF members) (Box 4)
  - Videotapes (Box 5)
    - Conferences
      - 1985
        - "Striving for Excellence"
          - Morning Keynote Address, Carmen Harlan (Box 5)
          - Afternoon Keynote Address, M. Tirado (Box 5)
      - 1986
        - "Focus on Effectiveness, Productivity, and Professionalism"
          - Keynote Address, Rose Martin (Box 5)
      - 1987
        - "Working Constructively Toward the Future"
          - Introduction, Awards, Morning Keynote Address Part I, Laura I. Rendon (Box 5)
          - Morning Keynote Address Part II (Box 5)
          - Afternoon Keynote Address, Susan Watson (Box 5)
      - 1988
        - "Imagine What We Can Be: Challenge, Create, Celebrate"
          - Morning Keynote Address, Dr. R. Griffin (Box 5)
          - Closing Ceremonies, Closing Speech, Awards, Part I (Box 5)
          - Closing Ceremonies, Closing Speech, Awards, Part II (Box 5)
      - 1989
        - "Shades of Quality: Emerging, Excelling, Empowering"
          - Keynote Address, A. Deer, and fashion show (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous
      - "Women of Color: A Success Story" (Laurita Thomas) 1986 (Box 5)
      - Women of Color Fashion Show 1988 (Box 5)
      - Interviews with 1987-1988 co-chairs (A. Gaines and E. Armstead) and 1987 Women of the Year winners (G. Spencer, L. Thomas, M. Craig, and K. Kelsey), 1988 (Box 5)
- Administrative (1991-2008)
  - ABPAFS/CEW/HRAA/OTCS/WCTF Partnership, 2004 (Box 6)
  - Agendas and Minutes
    - Executive Team, 2003-2006, 4 folders (Box 6)
    - General Membership, 2003-2008, 9 folders (Box 6)
    - University Sponsors, 2005 (Box 6)
  - Association of Black Professionals, Administrators, Faculty and Staff, 2003-2006 (Box 6)
  - Bylaws and Mission, 1991-2005 (Box 6)
  - Committees
    - Bylaws Committee, 2006 (Box 6)
    - Marketing Committee, 2003-2004 (Box 6)
    - Mentoring Committee. 2006 (Box 6)
  - Corporate Sponsors, 2002-2005 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence
    - Executive Team, 2003-2004 (Box 6)
    - General, 2003-2004 (Box 6)
  - Diversity Council "Observations on Racial Climate for Staff at the University of Michigan", 2004 (Box 6)
  - History
    - General, 1987-2006 (Box 6)
    - Interviews, 2003 (Box 6)
  - King-Chavez-Parks Visiting Professor Nominations, 2003-2004 (Box 6)
  - Monthly Reports, 2003-2005 (Box 6)
  - Newsletter Production, 2006 (Box 6)
  - Organizational Structure and Directories, 2004-2008 (Box 6)
  - Treasurer's Report, 2006 (Box 6)
- Archived Website
  The Archived Website series (64 KB, 2005) documents the mission, principles, and activities of the Women of Color Task Force as presented on its public website. Content includes information on the history, mission statement, premises, and teams of the task force. The series is arranged chronologically and includes content captured by the Internet Archive starting in 1997 as well as a capture provided by Bentley Library archivists in 2005.
  - 1997-2005
    (These versions were preserved by the Internet Archive and are made available through its Wayback Machine. The Bentley Historical Library is not involved in the collection or maintenance of this material.)
  - April 18, 2005, .ZIP file